RG 069:052, Wadsworth Family Collection
Connecticut State Library
Wadsworth Family collection
1718-1921
Connecticut State Library
Wadsworth Family
3 cubic feet
Wedworth Wadsworth (1782-1860) was a member of the Connecticut General Assembly from Durham, Conn. Also represented in the collection are his sons Wedworth (1811-1876), William (circa 1817-1870), a town clerk and justice of the peace, James (1819-1891) and James' son Wedworth (1846-1926), who was a painter, art teacher, and writer.
RG069_052
T001577
Biographical Note
The papers pertain mostly to the Wadsworth family of Durham, Connecticut, a prominent family headed by Wedworth Wadsworth (1782-1860). Wedworth's grandfather John Noyes Wadsworth (1732-1786) was the brother of James Wadsworth (1730-1817) who became a Brigadier General in the American Revolution and later an anti-Federalist during Connecticut's ratification proceedings. Wedworth was also the first cousin of Civil War General James Samuel Wadsworth (1807-1864) of Geneseo, New York who died at the battle of the Wilderness. Other family members include Wedworth's sons, Wedworth Wadsworth, Jr. (1811-1876); William Wadsworth (circa 1817-1870), Town Clerk of Durham and Justice of the Peace; James Wadsworth (1819-1891), Mayor of Buffalo, New York (1851) and New York state senator (1856-1859); and Wedworth, James' son (1846-1926) who became a painter, art teacher, and writer.
Scope and Contents
The papers include accounts, church papers, correspondence, court papers, deeds, estate papers, land papers, school society papers, tax lists, and turnpike papers. There are also writings, sketches and notes of Wedworth Wadsworth, the artist and writer. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by recipient, with the bulk addressed to Wedworth Wadsworth and William Wadsworth from family members who emigrated out of state. The majority of the court papers come from William Wadsworth's work as Justice of the Peace. The school society papers come from Wedworth Wadsworth's service as a trustee. The school society oversaw the operation of the Center, South, West, South West, and Quarry school districts. The tax lists include individual returns of Durham residents and property holders for 1865-66 arranged alphabetically by name. There are also individual tax lists for Wedworth, James, and William Wadsworth. The turnpike papers relate to the Durham and East Guilford Turnpike, of which Wedworth Wadsworth was a director. The Durham and East Guilford Turnpike Company was chartered in 1811 and operated until 1845. Included are early subscriber lists, accounts, and toll receipts.
Related Material
See RG 062, Records of the Towns and Boroughs, under "Durham".
See the Manuscript Collection (classified archival material), under "Wadsworth" and "Durham".
Index Terms
Subjects:
Land titles--Connecticut--Durham; Courts--Connecticut--Durham
Persons:
Wadsworth, Wedworth, 1782-1860; Wadsworth, Wedworth, 1811-1876; Wadsworth, William; Wadsworth, Wedworth, b. 1846
Places:
Durham (Conn.)
Occupations:
Artists; Town clerks; Justices of the Peace
Document Types:
Account books; Church records; Correspondence; Deeds; Essays; Illustrations; Land records; Poems; Probate records; Promissory notes; Receipts (financial records); School records; Scrapbooks; Tax records
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Container List
- Collection, 1718-1921
  - 1. Account books, 1812-1863, undated; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 2. Accounts, 1787-1867; 1921; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - General, 1787-1867 (Box 1)
    - Funeral expenses, 1921 (Box 1)
  - 3. Agreements, 1796-1863; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 4. Church papers, 1775-1859, undated; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - General, 1801-1854, undated (Box 1)
    - Meetinghouse construction and maintenance, 1783-1848, undated (Box 1)
    - Parsonage construction, 1820-1859, undated (Box 1)
    - Pew controversy, 1775-1833, undated (Box 1)
  - 5. Correspondence, 1797-1900, undated; 14 folders
    - General, 1797-1870, undated (Box 2)
    - Lyman, Betsy and Frances, 1817-1834 (Box 2)
    - Wadsworth, James, 1842,1852-1855 (Box 2)
    - Wadsworth, Lois, 1804-1827, undated (Box 2)
    - Wadsworth, Wedworth, 1804-1859, undated (Box 2)
    - Wadsworth, Wedworth (artist), 1895-1900 (Box 2)
    - Wadsworth, William, 1833-1870, undated (Box 2)
  - 6. Court papers, 1748-1869, undated; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - 7. Deeds, 1720-1900, undated; 10 folders (Box 3)
  - 8. Estate papers, 1792-1881, undated; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 9. Indentures and leases, 1794-1863, undated; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - 10. Land papers, 1718-1848, undated; 6 folders
    - General, 1723-1845, undated (Box 4)
    - Memorandum book of notes, 1800 (Box 4)
    - Pistapaug land, 1718-1808, undated (Box 4)
    - Plan of roads in southwest Durham, undated (Box 4)
    - Survey minutes, 1847 (Box 4)
    - Swamp accounts, 1781-1848, undated (Box 4)
  - 11. Notes, 1800-1865, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 12. Politics, 1844-1869, undated; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - 13. Receipts, 1858-1863, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 14. School society papers, 1802-1855, undated; 12 folders (Box 4)
    - Bills and receipts, 1802-1855, undated (Box 4)
    - Bonds, 1808-1833, undated (Box 4)
    - Certifications, 1826-1853 (Box 4)
    - Dividends, 1819-1853 (Box 4)
    - Minutes, 1817-1845, undated (Box 4)
    - Petitions, 1821-1844, undated (Box 4)
    - Reports, 1813-1845, undated (Box 4)
    - Subscriptions, 1810-1845, undated (Box 4)
  - 15. Scrapbooks, 1860-1914 (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1864-1911; 1 volume (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook clippings, 1860-1914, undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 16. Summons, 1791; 1 folder (Box 5)
  - 17. Tax lists, 1814-1866; 20 folders
    - General, 1858, 1865-1866 (Box 6)
    - Wadsworth Family, 1814-1850, undated (Box 6)
  - 18. Turnpike papers, 1810-1829, undated; 9 folders (Box 6)
  - 19. Visitors book, Wadsworth Cottage, 1 volume (Box 6)
  - 20. Works of art, 1889-1913, undated; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Exhibition catalogues, 1889, 1901-1913, undated (Box 7)
    - Illustrations, undated (Box 7)
    - Illustrations and poems (Box 7)
      - "Leaves from an Artist's Field Book", undated (Box 7)
      - "Thro Wood and Field with Tennyson", undated (Box 7)
      - "A Winter's Walk with Cowper", undated (Box 7)
  - 21. Writings, 1893-1906, undated; 28 folders (Box 7)
    - Essays written on a trip to Europe, 1895 (Box 7)
      - "Introduction" (Box 7)
      - "The Famous Trip of the Deacon, the Elder, and the Artist to Jerusalem" (Box 7)
      - "Lisbon to Marseilles" (Box 7)
      - "Marseilles to Naples" (Box 7)
      - "Pompeii to Syracuse" (Box 7)
      - "Malta to Athens" (Box 7)
      - "Fair Cairo on the Nile" (Box 7)
      - "Jerusalem" (Box 7)
      - "The Deacon at Constantinople" (Box 7)
      - "Deacon Obed on the Hellesfront" (Box 7)
      - "Impressions of a La Touraine Tourist" (Box 7)
    - Manuscripts, 1893-1906, undated (Box 7)
      - "Art and the Jury", 1893 (Box 7)
      - "Art and the Jury", undated (Box 7)
      - "An Artist's Year, Chapter 7", undated (Box 7)
      - "Bread and Wild Honey", undated (Box 7)
      - "Field Work in Watercolor", 1893 (Box 7)
      - "Four Cousins at the Beach", undated (Box 7)
      - "The Haunt of the Gray Squirrel", 1888 (Box 7)
      - "The Scented Fields", undated (Box 7)
      - "To the High Priestess of the Katy-Dids", 1906 (Box 7)
      - "A Touch from the Swallow's Wing", undated (Box 7)
      - "The Wanderer", undated (Box 7)
      - "Where the Wild Grapes Grow", undated (Box 7)
      - Untitled, undated (Box 7)
    - Notes of cruise of "La Touraine", 1895 (Box 7)
    - Poem, "Ode on the laying of the cornerstone of the Durham Public Library", 1901 (Box 7)
    - Story, "From the Hills to the Sea", undated (Box 7)